https://youtu.be/WlZhdrTxx0E
https://youtu.be/WlZhdrTxx0E
MATT MCGARRITY: So last week we talked about claims and evidence.
Tuần trước ta đã nói về luận điểm và luận chứng
And we just finished talking more about evidence.
và vừa kết thúc phần luận chứng.
And that's really what we've been looking at.
Đó là những gì ta đã xem xét.
We've been looking at sort of the bricks of the
Ta đã xem xét các yếu tố của
speech, claims and evidence.
một bài nói, luận điểm và luận chứng.
But a wall is more than simply just a pile of bricks, it needs mortar.
Nhưng cũng như một bức tường không đơn giản chỉ là đống gạch, nó có cần vữa.
And that's what we're going to be talking about now, the role of
Ta sẽ nói về điều đó bây giờ, vai trò
structure in your speech.
của cấu trúc bài nói.
We're going to be focusing on this mortar of your speech.
Ta sẽ tập trung vào phần "vữa" của bài nói.
Specifically for the impromptu speech, we're going to be looking at
Đặc biệt với bài nói ứng khẩu, ta sẽ học về
introductions, transitions, and conclusions.
phần giới thiệu, chuyển đoạn và kết luận.
So as a way of working on introductions, transition, and
Nói về phần giới thiệu, chuyển đoạn và kết luận,
conclusions, I would like you have something prepped so you could just
tôi muốn bạn chuẩn bị gì đó để có thể
run a real quick introduction, or conclusion as the case may arise.
nhanh chóng tạo ra phần giới thiệu hay kết luận cho các trường hợp.
So you don't have to prep obviously, but I do think it is a good habit.
Bạn không cần chuẩn bị rõ ràng, nhưng tôi nghĩ đó là thói quen tốt.
So what I would recommend you do is go to that impromptu list on the class
Tôi khuyên bạn nên tìm danh sách đề ứng khẩu trên trang web khóa học,
website, and grab one of those, and just draft up a real quick speech.
chọn lấy một cái và nhanh chóng nháp ra một bài nói.
Or of course, you can go and make up your own impromptu prompt.
Hoặc tất nhiên, bạn có thể tự làm đề tài riêng của mình.
But go ahead and pull together a basic impromptu outline, so that it can
Nhưng hãy làm một dàn ý bài nói ứng khẩu cơ bản
sharpen our discussion of introductions, transitions, and
để việc thảo luận về mục giới thiệu, chuyển đoạn và kết luận
conclusions.
rõ ràng hơn.
So go ahead and do that now.
Hãy làm ngay bây giờ.
And in the next lecture, we'll start talking about introductions.
Trong bài giảng tới, ta sẽ nói về phần giới thiệu.